Guide to the Richard Pratt Collection, 1820-2005 AIS.1998.03
ULS Archives & Special Collections
- Richard Pratt Personal, 1940-2005; II.
  Series II contains non-professional personal materials of Richard Pratt. This series is organized into three sub-series. Sub-series 1. General Materials, 1940-1978 contains notebooks, elementary and high school writings and papers, notes, hike diaries, articles, passports, and correspondence regarding trips to Cuba and Quebec and the Draft Board. Sub-series 2. Family Correspondence, 1940-2005, contains correspondence between Richard Pratt's parents, Karl and Gertrude Pratt; correspondence between Richard and Ann Pratt and their children; and Christmas and Family Letters. The Christmas letters are sent once a year and include most of the family happenings for the years 1964-2004. Sub-series 3. Personal Correspondence, 1943-1999, includes Richard and Ann Pratt's personal correspondence and has been kept in original order. The first part of the correspondence is arranged chronologically, 1943-1962. The second part of the correspondence is arranged alphabetically by last name.
  - General Materials, 1940-1978; 1.
    - The Long Trail, 1940-1942 (Box 18, Folder 1)
    - Notebook, 1941 (Box 18, Folder 2)
    - "Silhouette", 1945-1946 (Box 18, Folder 3)
    - Diary, 1947 (Box 18, Folder 4)
    - English Paper, 1948 (Box 18, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence, Leonard Cluley, 1948-1950 (Box 18, Folder 6)
    - Writings, 1949 (Box 18, Folder 7)
    - Diary, 1949 (Box 18, Folder 8)
    - School Papers, 1949-1951 (Box 18, Folder 9-10)
    - Activities/Expenses, 1950-1958 (Box 18, Folder 11)
    - Essays, 1950-1951 (Box 18, Folder 12)
    - Grammar Notebook, no date (Box 19, Folder 1)
    - Notes/Writings, 1951-1952 (Box 19, Folder 2-4)
    - Essay, "A Review of Divorce Problems", no date (Box 19, Folder 5)
    - Notebook, 1951-1953 (Box 19, Folder 6)
    - Quebec Trip, 1952 (Box 19, Folder 7)
    - Cuba Trip, 1954 (Box 19, Folder 8)
    - Draft Board, 1954-1962 (Box 19, Folder 9)
    - Wedding, 1958 (Box 19, Folder 10)
    - Hike Diary, 1960 (Box 19, Folder 11)
    - California, 1961-1974 (Box 19, Folder 12)
    - Passports, 1963-1978 (Box 19, Folder 13)
    - Miscellaneous, 1947-1980 (Box 19, Folder 14)
    - Articles by Richard Pratt, 1959-1964 (Box 19, Folder 15)
    - Address Books, Semester at Sea, no date (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Family Correspondence, 1940-2005; 2.
    - Karl and Gertrude Pratt to/from Richard Pratt, 1941-1951 (Box 20, Folder 2-11)
    - Karl and Gertrude Pratt to/from Richard Pratt, 1952-1954 (Box 21, Folder 1-8)
    - Karl and Gertrude Pratt to/from Richard Pratt, 1955-1959 (Box 22, Folder 1-10)
    - Karl and Gertrude Pratt to/from Richard Pratt, 1960-1964 (Box 23, Folder 1-10)
    - Karl and Gertrude Pratt to/from Richard Pratt, 1965-1974 (Box 24, Folder 1-18)
    - Karl and Gertrude Pratt to/from Richard Pratt, 1975-1983 (Box 25, Folder 1-18)
    - Karl and Gertrude Pratt to/from Richard Pratt, 1984-1997 (Box 26, Folder 1-13)
    - Family Letters, 1963-1983 (Box 26, Folder 14-21)
    - Family Letters, 1984-1994 (Box 27, Folder 1-11)
    - Family Letters, 1995-2005 (Box 28, Folder 1-11)
    - Christmas Letters, 1964-2004 (Box 28, Folder 12)
    - Richard Pratt to Mary Luella Pratt (Grandmother), 1940-1952 (Box 29, Folder 1)
    - Richard Pratt to/from Ann Pratt, 1955-1988 (Box 29, Folder 2-11)
    - Richard Pratt to Paul Pratt, 1974 (Box 29, Folder 12)
    - Richard Pratt to Kathy Pratt, 1974 (Box 29, Folder 13)
    - Richard Pratt to Jonathan Pratt, 1974 (Box 29, Folder 14)
    - Richard Pratt to "Children", 1974 (Box 29, Folder 15)
    - Ann Pratt to "Family", 1957-1959 (Box 29, Folder 16)
    - Richard Pratt to "Family", 1958-1980 (Box 29, Folder 17)
    - Postcards, Warszawa (not sent), no date (Box 29, Folder 18)
  - Personal Correspondence, 1943-1999; 3.
    - 1943 - June 30, 1956 (Box 30, Folder 1-9)
    - July 1, 1956 - June 2, 1962 (Box 31, Folder 1-5)
    - A-Bu (Box 31, Folder 6-8)
    - C - Fl (Box 32, Folder 1-5)
    - Fo - Gruenbaum (Box 33, Folder 1-6)
    - Gruver - Joseph (Box 34, Folder 1-6)
    - Ka - McDonald (Box 35, Folder 1-7)
    - McDowell - Po (Box 36, Folder 1-8)
    - Pratt - Sharp (Box 37, Folder 1-8)
    - Shaw - West (Box 38, Folder 1-7)
    - Wh - Zoran (Box 39, Folder 1-2)
- Sierra Club, 1973-1998; III.
  Series III contains materials related to Richard Pratt's involvement with the Sierra Club. Materials included are history, by-laws, publications, minutes from both the Pennsylvania Chapter and the Allegheny Group Executive Committee, and trip report forms that outline hikes and outings led by Pratt. This series also includes proposals, maps, publications, legislation, studies, and correspondence related to Pratt's involvement in the designation of wilderness areas in the Allegheny National Forest including the Allegheny Front and Tracey Ridge. Other materials pertain to Pennsylvania Scenic Rivers and Ohiopyle State Park. These materials are organized by subject.
  - Early History, 1974 (Box 39, Folder 3)
  - Bylaws, no date (Box 39, Folder 4)
  - Allegheny Sierran, 1973-1974 (Box 39, Folder 5-10)
  - Sylvanian, 1983-1994 (Box 40, Folder 1-6)
  - Sylvanian, 1995-1997 (Box 41, Folder 1-2)
  - Minutes, Pennsylvania Chapter, 1973-1983, 1991 (Box 41, Folder 3-6)
  - Minutes, Allegheny Group Executive Committee, 1974-1983 (Box 41, Folder 7-8)
  - Minutes, Allegheny Group Executive Committee, 1983-1992 (Box 42, Folder 1-3)
  - Allegheny National Forest, General, no date (Box 42, Folder 4)
  - Allegheny National Forest, Allegheny Front Proposals, 1973 (Box 42, Folder 5)
  - Allegheny National Forest, Allegheny River Face, no date (Box 42, Folder 6)
  - Allegheny National Forest, History, 1974 (Box 42, Folder 7)
  - Allegheny National Forest, East Hickory Proposal, 1973 (Box 42, Folder 8)
  - Allegheny National Forest, Local and Public Reaction, 1973 (Box 42, Folder 9)
  - Allegheny National Forest, Allegheny River Face Maps, no date (Box 42, Folder 10)
  - Allegheny National Forest, Minister Creek Proposals, 1973 (Box 42, Folder 11)
  - Allegheny National Forest, Miscellaneous, 1973-1982 (Box 42, Folder 12-13)
  - Allegheny National Forest, Other Proposals, 1973-1974 (Box 42, Folder 14)
  - Allegheny National Forest, Publications, 1970-1973 (Box 42, Folder 15)
  - Allegheny National Forest, RARE II, General, 1978-1979 (Box 42, Folder 16)
  - Allegheny National Forest, RARE II, East Wilderness Discussion, 1972-1974 (Box 43, Folder 1)
  - Allegheny National Forest, RARE II, East Wilderness Legislation, 1973-1974 (Box 43, Folder 2)
  - Allegheny National Forest, RARE II, East Wilderness Letters, 1977-1979 (Box 43, Folder 3-4)
  - Allegheny National Forest, Survey of Allegheny River Face, 1973 (Box 43, Folder 5)
  - Allegheny National Forest, Tracey Ridge, Study, 1973 (Box 43, Folder 6)
  - Allegheny National Forest, Tracey Ridge, Maps, 1973 (Box 43, Folder 7)
  - Allegheny National Forest, Tracey Ridge, Organization/Miscellaneous, 1973 (Box 43, Folder 8)
  - Allegheny National Forest, Tracey Ridge, OGM Information, 1973 (Box 43, Folder 9)
  - Allegheny National Forest, Tracey Ridge, Reports, 1973 (Box 43, Folder 10)
  - Allegheny National Forest, Tracey Ridge, Timber Sale Information, 1963-1973 (Box 43, Folder 11)
  - Allegheny National Forest, Tracey Ridge, Trails, 1974 (Box 43, Folder 12)
  - Allegheny National Forest, Trail Guides, 1974-1991 (Box 43, Folder 13-14)
  - Allegheny National Forest, Wilderness, 1977-1979 (Box 43, Folder 15)
  - Ohiopyle State Park, Laurel Run Study, June 30, 1976 (Box 44, Folder 1)
  - Ohiopyle State Park, Bruner Run and "Old Mitchell Place", no date (Box 44, Folder 2)
  - ECF Report, 1976-1978 (Box 44, Folder 3)
  - ECF EE Subpanel, 1977 (Box 44, Folder 4)
  - Forbes State Forest, 1973 (Box 44, Folder 5)
  - Pennsylvania Scenic Rivers, 1974-1978 (Box 44, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous Maps and Publications, 1976-1997 (Box 44, Folder 7-8)
  - Trail Segment Reports, 1975 (Box 44, Folder 9)
  - Vacation Guides, 1978 (Box 44, Folder 10)
  - Trip Report Forms, 1973-1998 (Box 44, Folder 11-13)
  - Trip Report Forms, 1973-1998 (Box 45, Folder 1-2)
- Pratt Family, 1820-1997; IV.
  This series contains the Pratt Family material including Karl Pratt professional or personal papers as well as the Pratt Family Photographs.
  - Karl Pratt Professional, 1920-1989; 1.
    Subseries 1. contains materials representing Karl Pratt's professional career. Karl Pratt was born November 20, 1899 in Huntington, Ohio. After graduating from high school in Wellington, OH, he went to Ohio State University, earning a B.A. (1923), M.A. (1924), and a Ph.D. (1927) in psychology. After earning his Ph.D. he was awarded an NRC fellowship at New York University, Karl finished his Ph.D. at Ohio State in 1927, and accepted a position at Central Michigan Teacher's College, now Central Michigan University, in Mt. Pleasant, MI. He taught psychology and eventually became the head of the department until his retirement in 1968. Some of his theories focused on early childhood (neonate) and progressive education.
    Materials include bibliography, resumes, articles, manuscripts, reprints, and article/book reviews. The bulk of this series contains correspondence. The correspondence is organized separately by subject and by individual (arranged alphabetically) and includes correspondence concerning publications and reviews. This series also includes correspondence from students, colleagues, and mentors.
    - Bibliography and Professional History, no date (Box 45, Folder 3)
    - Awards, 1927-1989 (Box 45, Folder 4)
    - Salary Letters, 1932-1967 (Box 45, Folder 5)
    - Writings, Manuscripts, and Notes, and, 1925-1946 no date (Box 45, Folder 6-9)
    - Unfinished Articles, no date (Box 45, Folder 10)
    - Notes on Articles about Infants, no date (Box 45, Folder 11)
    - Notes from Lectures, no date (Box 46, Folder 1-3)
    - Reprints of Published Articles by Karl Pratt, 1925-1946 (Box 46, Folder 4-5)
    - Reprints of Published Articles by Karl Pratt and Others, 1931-1954 (Box 46, Folder 6)
    - Reprints of Published Articles by Others, 1935-1944 (Box 46, Folder 7)
    - Article Reviews by Karl Pratt, 1936-1951 (Box 46, Folder 8)
    - Dissertation, 1930 (Box 46, Folder 9)
    - Manuscript - The Neonate (Box 46, Folder 10)
    - Journals Containing Articles by Karl Pratt, 1932-1938 (Box 46, Folder 11)
    - Journals Containing Articles by Karl Pratt, 1939-1940 (Box 47, Folder 1)
    - Manuscript - The 1936 Freshman -- 1940 Senior Class: An Analysis of the Effects of Selection and of Educational Gains and Losses, 1941 (Box 47, Folder 2)
    - Editorials by Karl Pratt, 1942-1962 (Box 47, Folder 3-4)
    - Correspondence Regarding Employment, 1923-1958 (Box 47, Folder 5-9)
    - Correspondence Regarding Professional Development, 1923-1980 (Box 47, Folder 10-12)
    - Programs - American Psychological Meetings, 1931-1935 (Box 47, Folder 13)
    - Superior State Teachers College, Wisconsin, 1950-1953 (Box 48, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence - Publishers, Students, 1927-1988 (Box 48, Folder 2-13)
    - Correspondence - Colleagues (A-S), 1920-1959 (Box 49, Folder 1-18)
    - Correspondence - Colleagues (S-W), 1932-1938 (Box 50, Folder 1-6)
    - Retirement Announcement and Correspondence, 1967-1968 (Box 50, Folder 7)
    - Tributes to Rowe, Herrig, and Poole, 1958-1967 (Box 50, Folder 8)
  - Karl and Gertrude Pratt Personal, 1911-1997; 2.
    While teaching at NYU, Karl met Gertrude, one of his students and ten years his junior (b. January 8, 1910). Their courtship and eventual marriage was opposed by both sets of parents on religious grounds. He was forced to return to Ohio State, after Gertrude's father met with the Dean at NYU - he was not fired, but his contract was not renewed. Gertrude completed her last year of college at Ohio State and Karl finished his Ph.D. in 1927 and accepted a position at Central Michigan Teacher's College, now Central Michigan University, in Mt. Pleasant, MI. In 1933, when Gertrude became pregnant with Richard she returned to live with her family in New York because Karl was not making enough money at Central Michigan to take care of her. She finally returned to Michigan when Richard was four. Gertrude worked as a bookkeeper, reference librarian for the college, recorder for the college, and as a reference librarian for Mount Pleasant Public Library. In 1968, Karl and Gertrude retired to the Camden, Maine area, where they stayed until Karl's death in 1993. In 1997 Gertrude moved to Pittsburgh to be closer to Richard but died within six months.
    Subseries 2. is organized into three sections. The first section contains general materials, 1911-1989, which includes elementary and high school diaries, manuscripts, account books, journals, and correspondence. These materials are arranged chronologically. The second section contains family correspondence, 1919-1997, and is organized chronologically by sender/recipient. The third section contains personal correspondence, 1919-1997, has been kept in original order. The first part of correspondence is arranged alphabetically by sender and each sender has a separate folder. The second part of correspondence is arranged alphabetically by sender but is grouped together by last name. The third section is arranged chronologically. The fourth and final section contains Christmas Letters, 1977-1987.
    - General Materials, 1911-1989
      - Elementary and High School Writings and Manuscripts, 1911-1921 (Box 50, Folder 9-11)
      - High School Journals, 1916-1920 (Box 51, Folder 1-2)
      - Diary - "Musings and Meditations", 1916-1920 (Box 51, Folder 3)
      - Account Books, 1919-1935 (Box 51, Folder 4-7)
      - Writings - "University Themes", 1921 (Box 51, Folder 8)
      - Daybook, 1924 (Box 52, Folder 1)
      - Letters to the Editor, 1922-1923 (Box 52, Folder 2-3)
      - Writings - "Miscellaneous Literary Attempts", 1925 (Box 52, Folder 4)
      - Hitchhiking Journal, 1925 (Box 52, Folder 5)
      - Manuscript and Publisher Correspondence - "Pale Shadow", 1931-1933 (Box 52, Folder 6)
      - Essay, "Exploration of the Long Trail", 1944 (Box 52, Folder 7)
      - Gertrude Pratt - Education and Employment, 1930-1980 (Box 52, Folder 8)
      - Gertrude Pratt - Book Reviews, 1930-1972 (Box 52, Folder 9-10)
      - Karl Pratt - Class Reunions, 1967-1982 (Box 52, Folder 11)
      - Karl Pratt - 90th Birthday, 1989 (Box 52, Folder 12)
    - Family Correspondence, 1919-1997
      - Karl to/from Gertrude Pratt, June 1929 - October 1933 (Box 52, Folder 13-16)
      - Correspondence, November 1933 - November 1937 (Box 53, Folder 1-14)
      - Correspondence, December 1937 - 1966 (Box 54, Folder 1-9)
      - Correspondence, no date (Box 54, Folder 10)
      - Karl Pratt to/from Mary Luella and Mildred Pratt, 1919-1928 (Box 54, Folder 11-16)
      - Karl Pratt to/from Mary Luella and B.H. Pratt, 1929-1963 (Box 54, Folder 17-18)
      - Karl Pratt to/from Mary Luella and B.H. Pratt, 1950-1963 (Box 55, Folder 1-6)
      - Karl Pratt to/from Mary Luella and B.H. Pratt, no date (Box 55, Folder 7-10)
      - Karl Pratt to/from Grandma Chapman and Houghton, 1919-1924 (Box 55, Folder 11-12)
      - Maud Chapman, 1951-1960 (Box 55, Folder 13)
      - Gennis Family, 1966-1972 (Box 55, Folder 14)
      - Joe and Sylvia Gennis, 1931-1989 (Box 56, Folder 1-2)
      - Bob and Christine Gennis, 1983-1984 (Box 56, Folder 3)
      - Bob and Mildred Gennis, 1952-1964 (Box 56, Folder 4)
      - Alvin and Bess Gennis, 1931-1951 (Box 56, Folder 5)
      - Sid and Sylvia Gennis., 1972-1973 (Box 56, Folder 6)
      - Kathryn Glass, 1962-1966 (Box 56, Folder 7)
      - Jonathan Pratt, 1965-1997 (Box 56, Folder 8-13)
      - Kathy Pratt, 1969-1979 (Box 56, Folder 14)
      - Kathy Pratt, 1980-2001 (Box 57, Folder 1-5)
      - Caroline Pratt, 1968-1997 (Box 57, Folder 6-11)
      - Paul Pratt, 1975-1990 (Box 58, Folder 1)
      - Letters to Karl Pratt while at OSU, 1920-1928 (Box 58, Folder 2-3)
    - Personal Correspondence, 1919-1997
      - "Troublesome Days at NYU", 1929 (Box 58, Folder 4)
      - Bakes - Menzes, 1919-1927 (Box 58, Folder 5-17)
      - Myers - Yarbush, 1919-1928 (Box 59, Folder 1-5)
      - Miscellaneous, 1922-1928 (Box 59, Folder 6)
      - Correspondence, A - E (Box 59, Folder 7-11)
      - Correspondence, F - Harrigan (Box 60, Folder 1-7)
      - Correspondence, Haw - Miller, Evangelene (Box 61, Folder 1-8)
      - Correspondence, Miller, Evangelene - R (Box 62, Folder 1-9)
      - Correspondence, S - Z (Box 63, Folder 1-7)
      - Correspondence, 1930-1975 (Box 64, Folder 1-10)
      - Correspondence, 1976-1991 (Box 65, Folder 1-16)
      - Correspondence, 1951-1990 (Box 66, Folder 1-2)
      - Christmas Letters, 1977-1987 (Box 66, Folder 3-4)
  - Pratt Extended Family, 1820-1960; 3.
    Subseries 3. contains materials, mostly correspondence, from other members of Pratt's extended family. Family members include Burton and Mary Luella Pratt, Richard's Grandparents; Benjamin and Alta Pratt, Burton's Brother, and various other Pratt, Gennis, and other family members. Some of this material dates back to the 1820s and 1850s and includes correspondence, notebooks, account books, invitations, manuscripts, and other materials, 1820-1960.
    - Transcribed Family Correspondence, 1861-1916 (Box 66, Folder 5-6)
    - Benjamin Pratt - Account/Expense Book, 1820 (Box 66, Folder 7-8)
    - Benjamin and Alta Pratt, Notebooks, 1840s (Box 66, Folder 9)
    - Benjamin and Alta Pratt, Account and Day Books, 1850-1873 (Box 66, Folder 10)
    - Benjamin and Alta Pratt, Receipts, 1859-1865 (Box 66, Folder 11)
    - Benjamin and Alta Pratt, Correspondence, 1855-1888 (Box 66, Folder 12)
    - Valletti to Alta Pratt, Correspondence, 1870-1891 (Box 66, Folder 13)
    - Luella Pratt to Alta Pratt, Correspondence, 1859-1864 (Box 66, Folder 14)
    - Miscellaneous, Correspondence, 1854-1900 (Box 66, Folder 15)
    - Invitations, Correspondence, 1883-1921 (Box 67, Folder 1)
    - Jerome Pratt to Benjamin and Alta Pratt, Correspondence, 1874 (Box 67, Folder 2)
    - Obituary, Benjamin Pratt, May 4, 1887 (Box 67, Folder 3)
    - Burton and Luella Pratt, Correspondence, 1874-1951 (Box 67, Folder 4)
    - Otis (O.C.) Pratt to Burton Pratt, 1918 (Box 67, Folder 5)
    - Jerome (J.B.) Pratt to Burton Pratt, 1907-1934 (Box 67, Folder 6)
    - Invitations, Burton and Luella Pratt, 1872-1937 (Box 67, Folder 7)
    - Burton and Luella Pratt, Manuscript - "Grumblers", no date (Box 67, Folder 8)
    - Jerome (J.B.) Pratt to H.J. Pratt, 1929 (Box 67, Folder 9)
    - Otis Pratt, Correspondence and Tombstone Inscription, 1908 (Box 67, Folder 10)
    - Orange (O.S.) Chapman, Correspondence, 1921-1922 (Box 67, Folder 11)
    - Hannah Chapman, Correspondence, 1920-1922 (Box 67, Folder 12)
    - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1855-1877 (Box 67, Folder 13)
    - Newspaper Clippings, 1891-1960 (Box 67, Folder 14-15)
    - Obituary, John Houghton, 1924 (Box 67, Folder 16)
    - Penmanship Book, no date (Box 67, Folder 17)
  - Pratt Family Photographs, 1860s-1965; 4.
    Subseries 4. contains photographs of Richard, Ann, Karl, Gertrude, and various Pratt and Gennis family members, 1860s-1960s. Inventories are available if noted at the folder level.
    - Richard Pratt, ca. 1934-1960 (Box 68)
    - Karl, Mildred, and Gertrude Pratt, ca. 1900-1965 (Box 69)
    - Pratt Extended Family, ca. 1862-1965 (Box 70)
    - Chapman, Houghton, Eaton, Needles, Pratt Families, ca. 1880s-1965 (Box 71)
    - Gennis Family, ca. 1920s-1965 (Box 72)
    - Photo Albums (with inventory), ca. 1934-1955 (Box 73)
    - Miscellaneous Photos, ca. 1880s-1965 (Box 74-78)